[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software for software engineering radio
this is Robert blumen I have with me
Christian mesh he has worked for 14
years as a software engineer including
space scope Science Institute he is the
tech lead on the open tofu project which
will be the subject of our conversation
today Christian welcome to software
engineering radio thanks for having me
apologies if my voice is a little bit
raspy I'm just getting back from cucon
where I gave a couple talks on open tofu
and had a great time meeting a lot of
the users and developers there it was
excellent yeah well a lot of talking
goes on at those events that's for sure
was there anything else about your
background you'd like listeners to know
sure I've worked at a variety of
software jobs at a variety of levels
throughout the industry although I will
say my time at open tofu has so far been
remarkably unique it's an opportunity
for me to work on a project that I've
cared about for quite some time and this
is going to sound cheesy but fight for
the user my main goal day in and day out
is making a project that works for the
people who are trying to use it I and
the other developers are all service
focused focused on figuring out what we
can do to make other people's lives
easier and being in that role day in and
day out is fantastic thank you open tofu
is a fork of the terraform project we
have covered terraform previously in
episode 289 and 405 on terraform best
practices before we go into open tofu
can you explain what terraform is sure
terraform is a tool that is used to
manage infrastructure infrastructure is
code you are able to define a
configuration which then talks to
whichever cloud provider or even the
pizza placed down the road using the
provider framework to deploy and manage
your infrastructure it's based on a
relatively simple declarative
configuration language pioneered by hash
Corp and it really took the ISA World by
storm a decade ago and has been adopted
throughout the industry both through
open source and close Source projects
its success resulted in a number of
companies being built around it and
built on top of it and that that will
kind of tail into some of the other
things we talk about today but as an end
user for someone who's not familiar you
write a config file saying I want this
infrastructure between these clouds or
these particular areas apply it and it
then goes and does it for you so instead
of having to go through the AWS console
or the gcp console and do all that by
hand it is a way to manage that
infrastructure as a team in code in a
pretty straightforward fashion in your
response providers came up can you
explain the boundary between terraform
and
providers and where do the providers
come from sure providers are based on a
specification put out by hashicorp they
have a grpc protocol and now that's
that's a technical detail it doesn't
matter too much but it is a standardized
protocol that many people have adopted
so at a higher level a provider is
something that allows you to talk to
some other service so open tofu and
terraform don't understand what AWS or
gcp is out of the box there's a little
caveat there but for the most part they
don't understand how to manage your
infrastructure they understand their
configuration language and they
understand how to download providers
providers then say hey I can manage for
example uh AWS ALB I can manage an S3
bucket I can manage resources on Google
Cloud so it is the bridge between your
configuration and open tofu to their
infrastructure tform is very well known
for provisioning cloud service providers
the two that you mentioned just now AWS
and gcp but it's not limited to cloud
services it can really provide almost
anything correct that's correct one of
the folks I work with on a regular basis
uses it to build thousands of Docker
containers it's not a standard use case
but it's fascinating to see all the
different ways people can use these
tools so a couple more notes on
providers they are written by both
hashicorp originally they're originally
all built into terraform back in the day
but they decided to break it out to make
it easier to author providers so if
you're a smaller cloud or you have
infrastructure on Prem or some other
scenario you write some go code that
tells open tofu and terraform exactly
how to manage that infrastructure the an
open protocol there's as last count
about 4,000 in the open tofu registry so
it's there's a few of the large ones
that hashicorp maintains themselves with
help from the community and from the
corresponding cloud provider but it's a
gamut spanning pretty much every corner
of software engineering and
infrastructure open tofu started out as
a fork of the terraform project which is
and may still be open source I'm not
completely clear about that can you
explain why open tofu Founders felt the
need to Fork off of terraform sure so
I'm going to step back in time a little
bit to go back to something I said
earlier about how this was started by
hasher Corp so they started this project
they created terraform they created the
providers back in the day and they
branded themselves as open source
Community focused and a lot of people
were comfortable adop in because of that
Focus that's one of the reasons they
were able to take the World by storm
unfortunately what happened is about a
little bit over a year ago hashicorp
decided to change the license on
terraform and they can do this because
of something called a contributor
license agreement so when you change a
license on a software project you need
to get sign off from all of the
contributors that have contributed code
in most cases that's what the license
requires so when I as a developer
contribute code to Project X if I have
not signed off on a license change they
cannot relicense the whole project they
can try and remove my contributions and
then work around that but it's the idea
that the license is in most cases fairly
immutable unfortunately the contributor
license agreement means that as soon as
you're contributing code to Hash Corps
terraform or a lot of other projects
we've seen mongodb elastic search
there's a large number in the past five
years that have effectively pulled the
rug out from under their communities so
in the terraform case in particular they
switch to something called their
business license now that is again I'm
going to preface a lot of things I say
today with I'm not a lawyer I'm not
speaking on behalf of any lawyers or
anyone who knows more about this but my
understanding and based on their FAQ is
it's it's not truly open source anymore
it is visible source which means they
have additional constraints on who can
use the software who can contribute to
the software which is a problem so the c
means that they can change the license
to whatever they want functionally
speaking they could move it close Source
if they wanted to they did a step in
which is a really tricky move to get
around and to work with so as open tofu
just as a concrete example we can't use
llms in any part of our process because
the code is visible but it is unclear if
the llm learns off of terraforms code on
GitHub what if someone contributes code
open to if we're using an llm does that
constitute a license violation we don't
know and it's an illegal gray area as
far as the enforceability of terraforms
license I can't really speak to that but
this is a pattern we've seen more and
more in software companies starting an
open source project getting a lot of
recognition and following because of it
because the community is helping build
it they see ownership of it they see
that it is a project they can contribute
to that they can build on top of when in
reality if it's one company with a
contributor license agreement that might
not actually be the case and
unfortunately we've been seeing that a
lot are the companies that founded open
tofu is there a specific worst case
scenario that they're imagining might
happen or is it more simple a lack of
clarity about what could happen and that
in itself is a bad thing so there's a
mixture of a lack of clarity and
explicit terms within the license and
their FAQ that mean that a lot of the
companies that sponsor open tofu not all
but many of the companies that sponsor
open tofu I'm going to say are fairly
sure that they cannot run modern
versions of terraform in their
infrastructure again this is a very
complex legal area but to the
interpretation of the companies that
have found it to who many of them are
uncomfortable running terraform in their
infrastructure and there's a pretty
strong sentiment that this was one of
the main reasons for the license change
so taking it as a step back terraform
has a corresponding product at hash Corp
that is in the form of their Cloud
offering that is it is something that
hashicorp is trying to push as one of
their big products they try and get
people to use it to store and manage and
run their infrastructure so instead of
running terraform on your developer
laptop you'll run it as part of
terraforms cloud and or hascs cloud and
there are some distinct advantages to
that what ended up happening is with any
product there is always room for
Innovation so a number of these
companies before the license change spun
up around terraform now sometimes it was
adding on functionality that didn't
necessarily overlap with what hash Corp
was offering in other cases it was a
indirect competition they're in a lot of
cases building similar features in these
hosted platforms so by changing the
license hash Corp made what I would
consider an anti-competitive move that
was trying to block other people who
were using terraform out of the market
and all their customers there in so open
tofu was a direct response to that a lot
of these companies are direct
competitors so you have nzero spacelift
harness and there's others that are in
this space and apologize it's been a
busy week coming back from cucon but a
lot of these companies saw the writing
on the wall they say this is no longer a
platform we can build upon this is
something that is risk to us and to our
customers it's unclear what the license
implies for both parties and again I
can't speak to that directly so the day
that this happened the founders of these
companies that had built on top of
terraform got together and put together
the manifesto they they broke down
barriers again these companies they're
trying to build the best product so that
they can win their other competitors
customers it's a competitive environment
this is what the foundation of open tofu
is and all those barriers were set aside
in a day after the license change
happened lines of communication were
opened and a Manifesto was created it's
currently on the front page of the open
toop website because a fork is the last
option ideally you want to work with the
community you want to figure out a way
forward unfortunately that Manifesto
fell on deaf ears and we were forced to
Fork the codebase after terraform 155
which was the last open- Source version
under the Milla public license and spun
up a team that I now lead that builds
new features on top of open tofu there
are some additional complexities to that
but open tofu is currently under the
Linux Foundation the trademark the
organization and it's also if someone
disagrees with even how the Linux
Foundation is running it open tofu is
easy to Fork this is by Design this is
kind of a demilitarized zone between
these companies and it's allows it to be
sponsored very heavily by these
companies but community-driven and I I
can talk more about that later if you'd
like let's talk about the open tofu or
you talked a little bit about what
motivated it to start what are some of
the founding companies okay if you don't
remember all of them sure we do have a
sponsor ship page on our website that
lists all of the companies involved off
the top of my head because these are the
ones that are actively contributing to
like have signed up to contribute to
developers whereas it's not which
doesn't cover all of the contributions
to open tofu but the developers working
on it spacelift who sponsors my
development harness nzero grunt work and
scaler those are all companies that are
sponsoring developers directly on it any
key points from the manifesto that you
have not already covered I don't believe
so other than it was the Olive Branch to
say listen we think you're making a
mistake by changing this license we've
all invested we've evangelized this
product we have built on top of this
product we've contributed back to this
product hash Corp had this narrative
that oh yeah we're all these other
companies are freeloading on top of
terraform but in reality it's become
increasingly hard to contribute back to
terraform in any fashion and that's one
of the reasons that as soon as open tofu
repo was created we got a delu of PRS we
couldn't accept all of them right away
but that's why there was so much
Community interest right off the bat
because it's open and we're more willing
to have I mean this is my personal
opinion that we're more willing to have
conversations about what the future of
the tool is and don't have a strong idea
of what open tofu should be in the
future other than community-driven we
will later in this interview talk about
of course the features in open tofu I am
also going to ask you if you recall any
of those PRS in that original delu let's
put that on hold for a moment and stick
with open tofu it has some kind of
corporate identity as an org what is the
nature of the org does it have employees
that's a good question so currently
there is a I'd call it maybe a coalition
I don't have the proper word for this
but there's an organization of companies
that came together that realized that
they needed a project that is truly open
source that they can build upon and that
that's what open to is as far as the
day-to-day organization there's a lot of
people involved in the peripheral but
primarily there are the engineers
that are the core team which I lead
which are from all of those companies I
mentioned before that handle reviewing
PRS triaging issues figuring out what
the next couple steps of the road map
are we're doing support in the slack
channel on GitHub above us is the
technical steering committee it's
currently comprised of a member from all
the companies that are currently
contributing engineering resources to
open tofu they meet once a week they
take a look at the road map any
technical issues or legal issues that
come up and decide either to try and
figure it out themselves and give their
core team guidance or to escalate to the
Linux Foundation at the end of the day
the bug stops with the Linux Foundation
they have a lot on their plate and lots
of projects so we try not to be too much
of a thorn on their side but anytime a
major change to our governance any
projects happens we run up by them first
because the goal is that no one company
no one individual has control of open
tofu that is one of the core tenants of
what we believe and the level of freedom
I have as Tech lead I'm I'm a spacelift
employee and this is one of the jokes I
told at Kon which is frankly true is I
don't know what spacelift is I've read
their marketing page I know roughly what
their product entails but I can't speak
to how it compares to other tools in the
space they don't come to me saying hey
Christian we need this feature in open
tofu to push our agenda for the next
release of spacelift or I don't even
know what the release Cadence looks like
it is remarkably hands-off I was
actually quite skeptical when I first
joined the team that it was going to be
okay you get 20% to do what the
community wants and 80% to do what
spacelift wants but no I it shows that I
don't know what spacelift does all of
their customers come through the
standard issue pipeline get triage just
like any other person wanting something
out of open tofu it is truly a space
that it still surprises me that all
these companies devote all these
resources and are completely hands-off
to the future of open tofu it is what is
a community asking for how do we win
hearts and Minds that is our goal and
it's been remarkable to be part of a
team that's focused purely on that
version 1.5.5 of terraform was the fork
Point terraform is now one 19 something
open tofu's had a number of versions
would it be a goal to stay compatible or
are these now two products that
naturally will evolve in different
directions because different people have
the best idea of what they think it
should be that's an excellent question
it's an ongoing concern and a question
we get frequently currently we're aiming
to be as close to a drop in replacement
as possible as people migrate over we
recently had Fidelity they spoke at open
tofu day at cucon they migrated 00
environments over to open tofu really
without a single problem a couple people
had to update their aliases and their
shell scripts but other than that it was
a drop in replacement as far as the
future is concerned this is a
conversation we have every single day
both amongst ourselves in the core team
and with the community so actively
there's a discussion happening on Stacks
so grunt work which Builds on top of
terraform and open tofu has a concept
called Stacks terraform in 1.10 is
introducing something called stacks and
they have some patents around it which
makes things complicated and other
companies
have similar features it's unclear if
open tofu is going to implement
something similar itself or add
functionality that allows tools to be
built on top of it that can provide this
functionality there's there's always
this question of what role does open
tofu fill in the ecosystem is it closer
to assembly is it closer to like a wiy
wig editor like there's the whole gamut
within the ecosystem and it's an
interesting conversation to figure out
where open tofu is today and where it
should be going but again this is always
a conversation with the community as far
as me personally I'm hoping that we can
keep compatibility as long as is
reasonably feasible but as these two
projects diverge I don't know what
that's going to look like I know open
tofu has some features that terraform
doesn't have and I know the reverse is
true and we've had a lot of community
questions about one of our community
members has created something called can
i.f and that is slowly being built out
to sort of document the differences
between the tools especially as they
change over time this raises another
point in my mind which I understand is
not the focus of this interview we did
an episode on this podcast about
automated rewrites Ai and other kinds of
tooling when people have to migrate
enormous code bases from let's say
Python X to python Y and this area isn't
one that's actively under development in
the industry for many reasons that's not
really a question but you can respond if
You' like sure as far as the migration
for opu currently the only thing that
really happens is we have to replace the
provider address within the state file
as far as tooling built on top of open
tofu to help with migration I think
that's something we'll consider in the
future as the future sets to Verge again
with the compatibility promise oh this
actually something I should have
mentioned earlier is the compatibility
promise is something that both open tofu
and terraform have which terraform
created and when we forked we adopted
that says that we're going to maintain
compatibility with 1.0 we're not going
to be breaking backwards compatibility
amongst ourselves
which means there's going to be that
core future set that 95% of people use
day in and day out that is unlikely to
change within the next couple years as
far as new features go that gets a
little bit trickier of a conversation
but we'll handle that as it comes we've
been talking just now about
compatibility of Teri form earlier we
talked about providers which are written
by different people and they interact
through a RPC interface are providers
going to be compatible with both
branches of the fork or will providers
now also need to potentially fork and
potentially support two different cores
so at this point our plan is to maintain
compatibility with the existing protocol
hashicorp has been adding things to it
but I would be remarkably surprised if
they ever make a breaking change to that
protocol they have stuff in there that
goes back honestly probably close to
half a decade if memory serves where
they still support odd and old patterns
that were built back in the day so
you've got 4,000 providers written by
probably 3,000 plus companies and
individuals so making any breaking
changes to that protocol is I would say
ill advised tform has been adding
additional things to that protocol which
we've been adopting as needed because
that that is still published under the
MPL version two but as far as where we
go in the future open tofu may start
adding additional features that aren't
in terraform and figuring out how to
give providers an option to implement
that without completely destroying the
workflow or becoming incompatible with
terraform is a big problem we have to
solve we have some really brilliant
Engineers that are currently noodling on
it but grpc is a pretty flexible entity
and there's options that we have moving
forward but our main focus is on
honestly first and foremost is not
breaking compatibility with that
protocol that is as far as I'm concerned
set in stone but you can with things
being added on top of it but the
providers themselves I hope we maintain
a scenario in where they don't have to
choose open toe for aform and they can
be built for both the tooling may get
more complex but something like where if
your provider and there is a difference
between the two you might be able to
handle that with a branch in your code
say if we're in this environment do this
otherwise it's not supported yeah and to
add on to that one question I get very
frequently is when I'm switching from
open over to ter do I need to do
anything with the providers do I need to
change them I hear that there's this new
registry so what does that look like my
response is Hash Corp decided that when
they change the license on terraform
they also to make it in my opinion more
difficult to Fork they changed the terms
of service on the registry the registry
is what allows terraform and open tofu
to connect to GitHub to download the
providers that metadata was now locked
within hash corp's fault so when we
fored open to we had to build our own
registry and we scraped GitHub very
thoroughly to find any potential
providers and added it to our registry
so we now are effectively maintaining
two sets of metadata one which is the
terraform registry that hashr maintains
and the open tofu registry which open
tofu maintains and the Community can
submit providers and modules to but the
interesting thing is side effect is that
palumi one of the projects in the same
sphere is no longer able to use the
terraform registry and actually had to
switch over to use open tofu's registry
and we're happy to have them and we're
actively in talks with trying to break
some portions of open tofu out into
librar so that we can duplicate some
effort there but when you do migrate it
will be using a separate registry under
the hood which again was just one of
those fallouts from some of hash corp's
actions they took around the time of the
fork if I understand this the provider
Registries are kind of a proxy or a
layer in front of the open source
project on GitHub so a provider project
could use GitHub publish their work as
everyone does and then it could show up
as a provider in one or more Registries
terraforms open tofu or anyone else
without the project having to have two
versions or be in two places is that
correct that's correct exactly so what
the likely do if I was authoring a
provider today I would submit it to both
Registries terraform and hashr they have
their own license you agree to you sign
into your GitHub account and they
actually get a web hook set up within
your project that you fire off anytime
you do a release open tofu wasn't really
in the position to ask every single of
those 4,000 authors to go through and
set up a web hook for us so we took a
little bit of a different approach so
our registry we automatically scrape
pretty much the entirety of github's
projects that we know about we look at
the RSS feeds for releases and we
automatically update every single
provider and every single module and
there's I think 25,000 modules of memory
serves every 15 minutes so as a module
author let's say you just wrote a
provider for open tofu you publish a
release on your GitHub page you go to
open tofu you create an issue using the
template paste in your provider's name
hit submit one of the core team does a
quick review takes a look makes sure
everything looks good merges that in
which which is just a small little
metadata file and our registry is if
you're familiar with the Homebrew
registry we actually worked with some of
their developers when designing ours
it's based on existing patterns that
work well in open source so our registry
on GitHub is just a giant set of
metadata files and then every 15 minutes
if you publish a new release we pick up
on that via the github's RSS feed and
automatically publish the new version in
open tofu no additional configuration
needed from the side of a provider which
we're happy about we've talked a lot
about the history
infrastructure organizational structure
now I want to get into what the feature
differences are I have used a lot of
terraform and probably like every
developer and every software I had the
thought well I really wish it did this
or that thing and you can only add so
many features to anything and some
features might not work very well with
the existing set of decisions so I have
a list of some of the features that are
highlighted on the open tofu website
that are in
178 we could go through those or maybe
if you would like to highlight what you
think are some of the top new features
in open tofu we could start from there
and then I can ask you about others if
we have time sure yeah I can give a
quick overview of some of the bigger
pieces of work we've done so far there's
lots of small little quality of life
pieces that I don't need to get into
today but are things that have been
asked for for quite some time the
biggest thing for 17 was State
encryption we actually had a company I
believe it was a German bank send one of
their employees to join the open tofu
team for a few months to build this
feature because they were maintaining a
terraform Fork internally in order to
meet compliance to the best of my
knowledge before you go into this talk
about what is the state and why would
someone want it to be encrypted sure so
the state is a Json file it's really
it's a set of data that open tofu uses
as a this is the state I think the
infrastructure should be in so open tofu
deals with realities the reality of the
configuration that the user has written
the reality of the state which is what
it think it applied and it that's what
it thinks infrastructure should
currently look like and then there's the
actual whatever is out there in the
world that someone may have been
twiddling knobs on so open tofu when
running an apply action will refresh and
take a look at what is currently out
there it'll load the state for what it
thinks should be out there and it looks
for any changes from the configuration
since the last time it applied changes
so this data may include IP addresses
ports configurations Secrets there's a
lot of stuff in there that you probably
don't want other people getting their
hands on so we took the Approach at
least initially of saying that well you
might have a bucket where this is
encrypted like for example S3 you can
configure encryption there but perhaps
you want to store your encryption keys
in a different cloud provider of all
things just for added security or maybe
the solution of having it not encrypted
in transport is a problem so our
solution was client side state
encryption so set up your keys in the
open Doo configuration either passed in
Via environment variables directly in
the config which we don't recommend or
via the AWS or gcp key management system
and we have Provisions for rotating keys
and and all of that migrating to and
from encrypted States so we actually had
someone post a I don't know off the top
of my head but there was a blog post
about the time we started this work
where someone realized that hey if you
have automated pipelines that are add
certain commands to open tofu and
someone gets access to your state you
can actually change the list of
providers in the state file and have it
download and install providers that
potentially execute arbitrary code so
the the state is a very critical piece
of open tofu and it should really be
protected terraform has an answer to
that feature which is ephemeral that's
something we they're working on in 110 I
have not honestly looked at it in great
detail yet we will be evaluating when
we'll do something similar but when I've
talked about it in the past it's two
complimentary feature sets it's the
probably good idea to not store secrets
in the state in the first place but to a
certain degree your state is a secret it
is a how your infrastructure is
configured where it's configured all of
these details that if someone gets
access to that particular file that
might open up a door you might not
expect I asked you to pick some of your
favorites I want to talk about one now
this sounds really cool Dynamic provider
Define native functions why would
somebody need that what is it sure so
you've written some htl in the past I'm
sure you've probably run into
comprehension or manipulating data
structures so I'm going to take one
small step back real quick so terraform
in introduced a feature called provider
defined functions and that allows a
provider to say here's a set of concrete
functions that open tofu can call based
on the configuration so for example the
ads provider has the Arn pars it takes a
string and turns it into a easy to
manipulate Aron object at open tofu we
saw that there were some additional
hooks in the API that we could really
play with and what we now allow is you
to define a provider that will take
configuration
that it can then use to expose
additional functions now that could be a
function that is I can tell it what
availability Zone it's in it can say hey
this is a valid thing for this zone or
not or it could do policy inspection and
all sorts of interesting things the more
fun ones that we really prototyped with
is we have a go and Lua provider so
these are still experimental I'm hoping
to take some time in the next month to
make them not experimental but
effectively what you can do is write a
Lua file or even in line write Lua or go
and have that exposed directly as
functions you can call within your open
tofu configuration this means that if
you have a large policy that you're
manipulating if you have data structures
you're trying to let's say you're trying
to sort by a key that doesn't is really
hard to access or you just want to be
type safe let's say you want to have
this large let's say you this large data
structure in open tofu that you need to
pull apart and use in different areas
maybe it's coming from another data
source in open tofu right now prior to
this in open tofu you would really just
have to write a really horrible
spaghetti for comprehension structure
that was UN really untestable and un
ergonomic now you could have a go file
that ships with your configuration and
tests for it so you can have strictly
typed data manipulation in a language
you're familiar with inside of open tofu
that can really patch over some of the
gaps within the htl language itself I've
used terraform it has a library of
buil-in functions like the length of an
array or set intersection that are com
able to what many programming languages
offer as buil-in
functions they added modules in a
release quite some time ago which are
something like terraform functions but
there has always been missing the
ability to define a new function and
make it available as a first class
function I understand this now I missed
the feature where they added functions
that a provider could write and the
providers are usually implemented in go
so that would then give you the full
power of the go language to write
functions that are on the same level of
usability as builtins is is that all
correct so far yes that's correct and to
if you're using terraform at least
currently you can only you have to write
a full provider and have all those
functions defined ahead of time your
configuration doesn't get to choose what
those functions are what they look like
the dynamic part of this feature then is
able to load
functions that are provided at the
terraform runtime is that the Step Up
from the provider defined functions
that's correct effectively the provider
now serves as a bridge to whatever
language that you want currently we
support go and Lua but others have been
experimented with like someone could
write a JavaScript provider so you could
inline Define JavaScript functions or in
a separ file Define JavaScript functions
and their tests and then have those fun
function be directly exported and able
to be used just like the buil-in
functions within open tofu prior to this
conversation if you'd asked me five
minutes ago what is a provider I would
have said it's a
terraform adapter between the core and
something that has an API that affects
infrastructure sounds like you've
broadened the definition of Provider to
interface with really almost any
external code it doesn't have to call an
API on the back end yeah yes terraform
originally made the changes to the API
that that we then built upon and
extended you still need to write a
provider to do as that adapter but
providers themselves have been able to
do more things above the original idea
that is just they connect you to a
particular
API okay moving on to some of the new
features there was something that had
not been released at the time I was
researching called Static evaluation of
provider iteration can you explain what
that is sure that is one of the most
exciting features we've worked on so far
it's a big one that's one of the reasons
the one n release our one9 release has
been taking a while but we've got the
alpha out for that but what exactly does
this mean so static evaluation or early
evaluation as some people call it is the
ability to evaluate expressions before
the state is available so we originally
added early evaluation a static
evaluation in order to let you define
your sources for modules in a static
fashion so you could have a config file
that defines the version of all of your
modules so a module is a set of
terraform code or open tofu code that
gets pulled in when you initialize the
project and provides additional
functionality in an encapsulated way
these are usually published and
versioned but in a lot of cases you'll
be using 20 copies of the same module or
20 subsets of the same module throughout
your infrastructure and will want to
upgrade those all at the same time or
switch them to a different Source at the
same time so that's something that needs
to be known before the state is
available and in order to do that we
have a separate evaluation engine that
sits before open toofer really gets into
its its Groove doing its graph traversal
and actually doing the application
planning and application of changes
we've then realized we can expand that
and use that functionality in a bunch of
places
we support it in backends so your
backend configuration can be a little
bit more Dynamic you don't have to pass
it in via the environment command line
variables you can have it a lot more
integrated but my friend and cooworker
Ronnie she gave a talk at cucon about
this that I recommend taking a look at
but getting back to the original
question early evaluation means that
akin to a pre-processor but there there
are some differences but for providers
going with a concrete example you might
have the AWS provider and the AWS
provider only functions within a single
region so in order to do any sort of
multi- region configuration you need to
have multiple copies of that same
provider so you're copying and pasting
config additionally let you have a
module that you want to have that module
let's say you got 100 resources in there
or some complex configuration and you're
passing a bunch of information into it
from your route currently you have to
copy and paste that module and all of
its inputs and outputs as well which is
unfortunate so this is something that
has frustrated people a long time
terraform quite a few versions ago I
don't remember the exact revision added
a for each feature to the language such
that modules and resources can be given
a set of data that can then expand them
so you could have a what most people
would love is a resource per region
maybe a bucket per region unfortunately
each of those instances of the module or
the resource would previously have to
use the same exact provider so in open
tofu now as of 1.9 Alpha 2 you can add a
for each expression which is it's just
like think about it like a map of data
if you especially if you've used for
each in resources modules it's it's
effectively the same concept you can
have a provider which is configured in
one instance that's configured in
multiple different ways which you can
then refer to from a module or a
resource and give it a particular key to
use so you could have a one of the best
examples is the ads provider config
configure that for five different
regions and then create a resource that
uses a for each expression as well and
that will then use that provider and
connect that resource instance to that
provider instance so your bucket in US
east1 is connected to the provider in Us
East one in order for that to function
you've effectively removed the giant
foot gun of copying and pasting your
configuration for every single region
there's a lot of other examples of this
but that's that's the one that's most
people will be familiar with in some
fashion and it is one of the it is the
top voted issue in open tofu and is I
think top five and has been for the
better part of I think at least five
years in in terraform let me see if I
understood that I'm aware with AWS it's
not only that I need an AWS provider but
the provider connects to a specific
region of correct AWS I might be
building out infrastructure that spans
multiple regions so I would need a
different instance of the AWS provider
for each region but other wise a lot of
code might be the same as a programming
problem generally I would say okay I'll
write a loop or a dict or something that
just assigns the regional provider to
run on the regional object that turned
out to be not straightforward to do
until this changed because the
evaluation which provider you use was
more static or came too early in the
runtime how did I do that's it exactly
that information needs to be known
really before you get too deep into
evaluation of open tofu but evaluating
the configuration in the state by adding
this early evaluation feature we can
figure out what providers we have ahead
of time and we can be a little bit smart
on what's being used where there are
some limitations to early valuation for
example you can't have a provider that
depends on data in the state for that
for each like the the for each
expression cannot depend on like results
from a query from a database or
something of that nature that raises
another question that might have fit in
earlier had I thought about it as far as
the different kinds of shared resources
that you bring into a terraform project
we talked about the terraform itself
providers there are also libraries of
shared modules that you you can do
things like there's an AWS VPC module
that will create a VPC with subnets and
you can have gateways all the typical
things you might or might not want to
have these are also open-source projects
that are maintained on GitHub can be
loaded into terraform to what extent are
the existing ecosystem of modules
compatible with open tofu and do the
module writers face the need to possibly
Fork that's an excellent question
currently we support the same modules
again this is it depends on the language
and we haven't really changed the
language in too dramatic of a way
there's a couple new features that exist
on one side of the other that folks need
to be aware of but in practice most
people don't need to worry about it
today but one thing we did add is
something called the tofu file extension
this file extension looks is almost
identical to the TF extension but in
open tofu it has a special meaning and
terraform just ignores it so if I'm a
module author and I want to use a new
feature that might be slightly different
in one of the few cases between open
tofu and terraform I can have a
terraform file that gets overridden by a
tofu file only when being run by open
tofu they can kind of use that as a in
the same Branch with the same code I can
support both and just use that as sort
of like a feature flag one way or the
other it's also worth noting that jet
brains in their latest release I think
they just put this out a few days ago
they added full support for the tofu
file extension and we're working
actively adding support for some of the
other new features that concept reminds
me of the overlay pattern that you see
in a number of places it's pretty common
in kubernetes with yaml or with system D
services you can create a overlay file
that overwrites a specific portion of a
default without having to edit the
original do you know if you were
inspired by this pattern in any other
software not off the top my head it's
more so replacing the entire
configuration file there's something a
little more similar to what you
described which are the underscore
override files those are more used if
you're honestly I don't I don't
recommend you use them they're not
terribly well supported in either tool
but like so if you do underscore
override after the file name or after
the file name before the extension it
Flags some interesting function ity
within both open tofu and terraform but
the main thing is for the tofu file
extension is it's a pretty simple set of
rewrite rules where if the file exists
open tofu will load that. tofu file over
that. TF file and in terraform at least
today they completely ignore the tofu
file we haven't covered all of the new
features but we're running short on time
either we could talk about one more new
feature or in the Deluge of PRS that
came into open tofu were there any ones
that you remember as being significant
I think there's a few that stand out the
ones I get really excited about are the
performance improvements they're usually
interesting little puzzles that I get
that I then get to dive into but I think
it was more so the volume and the the
interest from the community the people
who were chomping it the bit to say I've
had something I've wanted to do with
this tool for a long time and I feel
like I finally have the opportunity to
do so I don't have too many specific
examples but I would recommend if
someone's curious take a look at the the
release notes the core team does a fair
portion of the work for every release
but we're consistently overwhelmed by
the amount of ideas and support coming
from the community does raise another
question is performance of the core
engine something that to open tofu is
trying to compete with terraform on it's
something that I don't know if it's a
direct competition if if that's the way
I'd put it but I think it's something
that's important to a lot of our users
and it's something that we focus on
there's a guy who frequently will send
me on the open tofu slack a profile of
his ridiculous setup and it's again it's
one of those things where he's it's not
necessarily we the way we recommend
someone use the tool but it's
fascinating what people use it to get
into and I'm happy to jump on and take a
look at that and try and fix that case
because I'm nine times out of 10 there's
someone else out there that's having the
same problem I will say there some
people have contributed to both open
tofu and terraform and performance is
one of those locations we had a a user
come in and submit PR to both open tofu
and terraform and at that point I guess
the code was similar enough that they
could send the same PR to both I didn't
look at the terraform side but in some
cases we do have the same performance
improvements in other cases I know open
tofu especially like for provider
functions takes a different path and
we've had some we've had a user
analyzing the performance there and in
some cases open tofu has a pretty big
Advantage honestly as far as where the
future goes I mostly just want to make
users lives easier and if that means
that we can reduce the cycle time that's
something to focus
I want to switch over now talking about
the road map talk about first how is the
community involved in the road map sure
I think the most visible way is the top
thing on our GitHub issues is a top
voted issues post that's been pinned
that is something that we look at pretty
much every day to see what users are
asking for so they can they can give
their thumbs up on an issue and that
directly corresponds to where it where
it lives in that list that allows us to
very quickly see what are users most
passionate about this isn't the the
final thing we look at uh sometimes if
there's something that one of the
developers gets really excited about or
if someone puts in a PR then that might
prioritize it as well but it is entirely
based on what the community is asking
for we do take a look at uh what
terraforms release notes have every time
they put a new release out and we take a
look in in within the core team what we
think would make sense to pull in out of
the box as far as features go again we
can't pull in any code but we can look
at
we can look at the release notes and we
can most of the time figure out roughly
what's going on there and Implement that
ourselves but we don't do that for every
single feature some of the new features
that are added to Providers we haven't
added for a releaser to because there's
not really anyone using them yet there's
a lot of stuff that's added to terraform
that is more focused on their Cloud
offering and what's going on there
whereas we're entirely focused on what
the community is looking for but if the
community comes to us and says hey
there's a discrepancy between open tofu
and terraform here or if there's a
feature that open tofu only implemented
part of because that was what they
thought the community wanted then we
we'll go back and include that in a
subsequent release the actual release
Milestone itself is comprised of a
number of issues that the core team is
interested in getting into the next
release but it's very fluid if the
community is very focused on performance
optimizations or adding certain new
features we'll change our plans for a
release we'll start pulling that in
reviewing those PRS and getting those in
and it's Dynamic we are not the ones
that have an idea of what open tof is
going to look like in five years that's
one of the hardest questions I have to
answer is we don't know and that's
that's intentional our job is to figure
out what the community is asking for
what the community needs and to build
the best tool for them and I I I know I
sound a little bit sappy there but
that's is what I believe can you pick
one issue on the road map that you think
is quite interesting or
worthwhile the one that that I look at a
lot is I tend to think about
improvements to
I mentioned earlier that open tofu
doesn't really understand what AWS gcp
and other Cloud providers are there's
one major exception to that which is the
backends a backend is something that can
a remote State back end is something
that stores the state so when you're
talking about your state file some
people just commit it and get other
people put it in an S3 bucket it can go
in a variety sometimes goes in a
database it's fluid but there's
currently a set of backends that are
built into open tofu but there isn't
there isn't a great way of someone
writing their own back end and there
there's some pretty significant
limitations of back end so if the ad API
changes or is enhanced in some way you
have to wait for open tofu to patch
itself and then push a release that
includes those changes so one of the
things is S3 added an option for locking
so that our Dynamo DB setup is no longer
needed that's something that will have
to go out in a release at some point but
it users will have to wait for that one
thing we're trying to work toward is
first building a better HTTP backend
that's something that exists today that
a lot of companies build around it
allows you to it's a relatively
straightforward HTTP protocol that says
it can accept a state file provide a
state file it can do locking mechanisms
those sorts of things but it does lack
some pretty significant functionality so
we first want to improve that then we
want to start writing a library to make
that easier once we have that library in
place with compliance tests and helping
people just build a backend that works
and is well tested once that's in place
our goal is to start looking at adding
grpc support to that mostly because
that's what open tofu uses to talk to
Providers and as the next stage start
looking at integrating that within the
provider protocol or something something
similar so it's shipped in the provider
binary or maybe as as an additional
binary that goes along with it we're
still the technical deta details on this
are still a little bit sparse because
we're still figuring it out and there's
a lot of different ways to go with it
but functionally speaking we'd love to
be able to ship a back end binary
similar to how we ship provider binaries
today where someone can say hey I want
to use this particular version of the
AWS API because it uses the type of
credentials that I'm familiar with and I
haven't had time to upgrade my my
organization yet this also means that it
takes burden off of the open tofu
developers we could move all those
backends into Community projects so it's
not within the open tofu day in day out
practice and people can upgrade them we
can release them asynchronously from
open toop releases if there's a new AWS
feature or gcp feature if someone finds
a bug and wants to patch it is doesn't
have to be locked to the same release
cycle similar to how providers are
flexible today do you have any data on
the adoption so far I do so open doof Fu
does not have Telemetry we immediately
rip that out as soon as the fork was
created but we do have stats for
downloads of both the B the open Doo
binary itself and for providers and
additionally the companies's built
around around open do have some internal
metrics so our actual downloads I'm I'm
taking a look at the space lift blog I'm
sure it's on some of the other after
open tofu day that's cubec con it has
been a pretty linear increase since we
started so we are in total weekly
downloads as of today we are at 250,000
downloads per day of open tofu how that
compares to tform they don't as far as I
know they don't publish that information
or if they do I'm not aware of it but we
have a it's been a fairly linear
increase and we've seen that both in
again the amount of downloads and the
number of issues on GitHub and the
growth of the community the part is
although I am around for supporting
users and the core team is around for
supporting users when they run into
issues either in open tofu or just the
the problems face in general a lot of
the time we're actually beaten to the
punch by other members of the community
because it's grown large enough that
they can they can help each other out
and I love to see it we mentioned open
to.org are there any other places on the
internet that you'd like to point
listeners toward I think at this point
open to.org is the main spot we have a
Blog we probably don't post as much as
we should but after open tofu day we
should have the videos uh from that day
that we'll be posting we'll also be
posting that on our YouTube channel and
we'll also occasionally post short
videos there showcasing new features and
we've even done a couple live streams
there just to give people a way of
chiming in live and reacting to stuff
we're working on so there's a open DOA
Community slack linked from open
toto.org and we also have a Google meet
that we do once a week as the core team
that we invite anyone and everyone from
the community to so we can talk about
what the core team's been up to what
we're trying to help different people in
the community with and just try and in
general answer questions kind of like
how we're talking today is there
anywhere listeners can find you so
primarily on the open tofu slack on the
open tofu GitHub I'm one of those
strange people who somehow has managed
to avoid creating a LinkedIn up to this
point but yeah if you've head over to my
GitHub cam 72 cam I have a Google
Calendar link there I welcome people to
just schedule a time to meet and talk
again I I enjoy listening to how people
are working with open tofu what
questions they have if they have any
ideas they want to talk through anything
and everything my schedule's pretty open
uh rather I can move my schedule around
well enough that yeah if you've got
ideas you want to talk about an issue on
GitHub you want to talk about ideas
you've got reach out and I'll be here
waiting excited for it Christian thank
you for speaking to software engineering
radio of course thanks for having me on
this has been a pleasure this has been
Robert bluman for software engineering
radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at
e-r. to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for listening